<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the Roman Church VVherin is treated, vvhether the said Church of Rome hath fallen in faith, or no? Written in Latin by the R. F. Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity: and now translated into English.</title>
            <author>Becanus, Martinus, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06531</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850790</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850790</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16017</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06531)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16017)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1090:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the Roman Church VVherin is treated, vvhether the said Church of Rome hath fallen in faith, or no? Written in Latin by the R. F. Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity: and now translated into English.</title>
                  <author>Becanus, Martinus, 1563-1624.</author>
                  <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini, M. DC. XII. [1612]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: VVhether the Church of Rome hath fallen, or no?.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:16017:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16017:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE ROMAN CHVRCH. VVHERIN <hi>Is treated, VVhether the ſaid Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath fallen in faith, or no?</hi> Written in Latin by the R. F. <hi>Martinus Becanus</hi> of the Society of Ieſus, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour in Diuinity: AND <hi>Now tranſlated into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anno Domini, M. DC. XII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16017:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16017:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OOD Reader, this ſhort Treatiſe being ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto me long ſince from a friend, who had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to be tranſlated out of Latin into Engliſh; I haue iudged it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be imparted vnto theo, for that it will giue thee light in a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which greatly importeth thee to know, and on which the Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do imploy their whole endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to caſt a cloud of obſcurity.</p>
            <p>The matter in Controuerſy is, <hi>Whether the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hath fallen from her ancient faith?</hi> The Proteſtants affirme the ſame: and if they could in place of often ſaying
<pb facs="tcp:16017:3"/> it, once proue it, their cauſe were much the better. The Catholiques on the contrary ſide deny, that She euer admitted the leaſt change in any point of faith. Which if thou find to be ſo, as by reading this little Phamphlet, I hope thou ſhalt, then haſt thou a cleere and ſure way laid before thee, to reſolue thyſelfe of all doubtes, that may concerne Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Beſtow therfore the reading ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and thou ſhalt find the profit to counteruaile thy paynes. And ſo wiſhing thee euerlaſting happines, I bid thee farewell.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16017:3"/>
            <head>WHETHER THE CHVRCH OF ROME hath fallen in faith or no?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſenſe hereof is, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Roman Church, togeather with thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here vnto it, hath ſo fallen and degenerated, that it ſhould ceaſe to be any longer a true Church? <hi>Iohn</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Inſt. c. 7. §. 24. v de. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c. 6. §. 26</note> 
               <hi>Caluin</hi> affirmeth that it hath ſo fallen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in theſe words: <hi>Fuerit ſanè olim Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma omnium Eccleſiarum Mater &amp;c.</hi> Verily <hi>Rome</hi> in times paſt, was the Mother of all Churches; but in that it hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be the Seat of Antichriſt, it ceaſeth to be that which it was. Here he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth two things. One is, that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church was ſometimes the true Church, and more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, that it was the mother of all Churches. This we
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:16017:4"/> admit. The other is, that it is now fallen and become the ſeate of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi> And of this we diſpute.</p>
            <p>2. Two wayes we may vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it to haue fallen. Firſt in <hi>Manners.</hi> Secondly in doctrine of <hi>Faith.</hi> The former defect taketh not away the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a true Church, but the later. This therfore is the State of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, <hi>VVhether the Roman Church hall</hi>
               <note place="margin">The State of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</note> 
               <hi>ſallen in doctrine of ſaith? Caluin</hi> affirmeth it hath thus fallen: neither doth he otherwiſe proue it, then by a groſſe &amp; manifeſt vntruth. For he ſaith, that longe agoe the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> haue taught 3. moſt greiuous errors tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Faith: to wit, <hi>That there is no God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. Inſt. cap. 7. §. 27.</note> 
               <hi>no Chriſt, no Reſurrection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. But I will contrariwiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, not by vntruths as he doth, but by ſtrong arguments, that the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as heertofore it was, ſo ſtill to be at this preſent, the true Church of Chriſt: nor euer to haue fallen away from her purity; and that three manner of wayes. 1. By Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. 2. by Fathers. 3. by <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelf and his owne principles. And that I may be briefe, I will vſe this laſt kind
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16017:4"/> of proofe moſt; eſpecially ſeeing that many others haue longe ſince both out of Scriptures &amp; Fathers very copiouſly handled the ſame argument. To the end therfore that the whole matter may be the more eaſily perceiued. I will labour to deduce, and explicate the ſame by certaine Concluſions. This then is,</p>
            <div n="1" type="conclusion">
               <head>The 1. Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THERE muſt be graunted ſome viſible Church on earth, which both is, and is alſo called Catholike, Holy, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the houſe of God, the Piller and firmament of Truth.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1 THIS concluſion is wholy gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Caluin</hi> in his 4. booke of Inſtitutions <hi>Chap.</hi> 1. for many para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphes togeather, where he purpoſely diſputeth of the Viſible Church. And verily in the 2. §. he affirmeth, that by Faith we belieue the viſible Church, when we ſay in the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>I belieue the Holy Catholike Church.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that a viſible Church be granted, is an article of Faith, according to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:16017:5"/> 
                  <hi>Caluin.</hi> And full rightly. For albeit we ſee with externall eyes, the multitude of thoſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherof the viſible Church conſiſteth: yet notwithſtanding that there is the true doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles in the ſaid multitude, this we ſee not, but belieue it. So that the viſible Church is conteyned partly vnder ſight, partly vnder Faith. With externall eyes we ſee thoſe men that be in the Church: with internall faith we belieue, that amongſt them the true doctrine of Chriſt is both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered and conſerued.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And thus is that Cauil of the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> ſolued: <hi>That which we belieue by faith, is not viſible. But the Church we belieue by faith. Ergo, the Church is not viſible.</hi> For the Maior Propoſition ought thus to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood: That which we belieue by Faith is not viſible, according to the thing that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined vnder Faith, although it be viſible according to ſome other thing, that is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined vnder Faith. And of this matter there be diuers exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. In Chriſt the Apoſtles ſaw his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, they belieued his Diuinity. In baptiſme we ſee the externall water and waſhing; but the internall force
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16017:5"/> of regeneration and remiſſion of ſinnes we belieue. In the volume of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, we ſee the paper, the writing, and the volume it ſelfe; we belieue that to be the word of God, which is read therin. The ſame iudgment therfore there is of the Church. Somewhat there is in it which we belieue; and ſomewhat which we perceiue by ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But leaſt that any ſhould be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, we muſt yet vſe another di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction. For it may be two wayes vnderſtood, that we belieue the Church by Faith. Firſt, that by faith we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that ech man which is in the Church, is truly faithfull, and doth with internall affection follow the doctrine of Chriſt. Secondly, that by faith we belieue the doctrine of Chriſt to be both taught, and conſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in it. The former ſenſe is falſe: the later is true. For we doe not belieue, that as many, as are in the viſible Church with vs, are according to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall affection, truly faithfull, becauſe it is plaine, that many hypocrits are in the Church, as I will ſhew you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes: yet doe we belieue that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16017:6"/> doctrine, which by externall voice the men that are in the viſible Church doe profeſſe to be that true doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, without which there is no ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And that this viſible Church is to be called <hi>Catholike, Holy, the Spouſe of Chriſt, the houſe of God, the pillar and firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Truth, Caluin</hi> confeſſeth §. 2. 9. 10. and the reſt that follow. And the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is certaine. For both Scriptures, Creeds, and Fathers teach ſo euery where. It is called <hi>Catholike</hi> or <hi>Vniuerſall,</hi> for three cauſes. Firſt in reſpect of place, becauſe it is ſpread ouer the whole world. Marc. 16. 15. <hi>Going into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> whole world, preach the ghoſpell to euery crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi> Secondly, in reſpect of <hi>Tyme,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſhall laſt for euer, Dan. 2. 44. <hi>The God of heauen will ſet vp a Kingdome, which shall neuer be diſſipated,</hi> or diſſolued. Thirdly in reſpect of the <hi>Men</hi> that are to be ſaued, becauſe no man can be ſaued out of the Church. Herby appeareth the difference betwixt the Church of Chriſt, &amp; the Synagogue of the Iewes. For the Iewes Synagogue was none of theſe wayes <hi>Catholike</hi> or <hi>Vniuerſall.</hi> Not the firſt way: for it was not ſpread ouer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16017:6"/> the whole world, but ouer <hi>Paleſtine</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Not the ſecond, becauſe it laſted but a certaine time. Not the third, becauſe men, out of the Synagogue, might be ſaued, as <hi>Iob,</hi> the <hi>Niniuites,</hi> and others were.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It is called <hi>Holy,</hi> for theſe cauſes, Firſt, becauſe no man entreth into it, vnleſſe he be waſhed and ſanctified by Baptiſme. And in this ſenſe the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaid, that Chriſt hath waſhed his<note place="margin">Eph. 5. 26.</note> Church in the lauer of water. And in another place: <hi>Theſe verily you were, but</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. v. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>we are washed, and ſanctified.</hi> Secondly, becauſe all her inſtitutions, worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, cerimonies, &amp; Sacraments are ordeined to ſanctity. For they tend to this, that wee either become holy, or that we increaſe, and be conſerued in holineſſe. Thirdly becauſe out of it, there is no holineſſe. Fourthly, becauſe Chriſt is her head, who is the Holy<note place="margin">Sanctus Sanctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </note> of Holies. <hi>Caluin</hi> §. 17. addeth, that ſhe is called <hi>Holy,</hi> becauſe ſhe profiteth in ſanctity dayly, and aſpireth to the very top, or butt of ſanctity.</p>
               <p n="6">6. She is called the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe Chriſt hath by an indiſſoluble band coupled her to himſelfe, as the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16017:7"/> Apoſtle teacheth <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. And ſhe hath<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 31. 32.</note> three priuiledges. The firſt is, that ſhe is fruitfull. The ſecond is, that ſhe is <hi>Euer a Virgin.</hi> The third is, that ſhe iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the ſide of her Spouſe. All theſe three taken togeather, neuer hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to any ſpouſe. <hi>Mary</hi> the wife of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was indeed both fruitefull, and euer a Virgin; yet did ſhe not come out of the ſide of her husband. Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, <hi>Eua</hi> was made out of the ſide of <hi>Adam,</hi> and was fruitfull; yet was ſhe not a perpetuall Virgin. But the Spouſe of Chriſt hath obtayned all theſe at once. And firſt, that is fruitfull, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by that <hi>Gal. 4. VVe are not the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the hand-mayde, but of the free-woman.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 31.</note> That ſhe is a Virgin, appeareth by that 2. <hi>Cor. 11. I haue eſpouſed you to one man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>to exhibite a chaſt Virgin vnto Chriſt.</hi> That ſhe came out of the ſide of Chriſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do gather out of that in S. <hi>Iohn</hi> 19.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>One of the Souldiers opening his ſide with a lance, forthwith there iſſued out bloud and water.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. It is called, <hi>the houſe of God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe although God be euery where, as himſelfe confeſſeth in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> ſaying,<note place="margin">Cap. 23. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>I fill heauen &amp; earth:</hi> yet is he ſaid to dwel
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16017:7"/> after a peculiar manner in the Church, as in his houſe, by his ſingular aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, gouernement, and diſtribution of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall gifts &amp; graces, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28. 20. This houſe he built for himſelfe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. 18. In this houſe, he hath a Diſpenſer, and Steward ouer his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, <hi>Luc.</hi> 12. 42. In this houſe he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth children by Baptiſme, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructeth and foſtereth them by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; and nouriſheth them with the Euchariſt. In this houſe he hath veſells of all ſorts, of gold, and of ſiluer, of wood, and of earth, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 20. In this houſe he celebrateth marriages &amp; maketh Nuptialls to his So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 2. Out of this houſe, or Church, there are neither lawes, nor miracles, nor Sacraments, nor Sacrifices, to wit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to ſaluation.</p>
               <p n="8">8. It is called <hi>The Pillar and Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Truth,</hi> both becauſe, ſhe is a <hi>faithfull Keeper of Gods truth,</hi> as <hi>Caluin</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playneth:<note place="margin">§. 10<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> as alſo, becauſe <hi>in no part of the world beſides, doth Gods truth dwell,</hi> but in the viſible Church, as <hi>Beza</hi> doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 15. as laſtly alſo becauſe ſhe can not erre from the truth, as Catholiks doe expound it. And thus
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16017:8"/> much concerning the firſt Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="conclusion">
               <head>The ſecond concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>IN this viſible, and Catholike Church, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue ſpoken, are all ſuch as are through Baptiſme admitted into the faith of Chriſt, not the good only; but the bad alſo: not only the predeſtinate, but alſo the reprobate.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1 THIS Concluſion alſo <hi>Caluin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4. c. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7.</note> admitteth in theſe words: <hi>But in this Church there are mixed many hyprocrites ambitious, couetous, enutous, &amp; euill ſpeakers.</hi> And §. 13. <hi>They alleage that Chriſts Church is holy: but yet ſo, as that withall they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it to be mixt of good and bad. Let them heare that Parable from the mouth of Chriſt, wherein She is compared to a net, in which all ſorts of fishes are gathered, but are not <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> or choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out.</note> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, vntill they be laid out vpon the shore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. All Catholikes do agree here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. We confeſſe (ſaith S. Auguſtine)<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ract. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Ioan.</note> 
                  <hi>that in the Catholike Church, are both good and bad, but as graine and chaffe.</hi> Againe. <hi>The Church hath in her ſtronge men, she hath</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erm. 107. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e temp.</note> 
                  <hi>infirme; she hath iuſt men, she hath alſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:16017:8"/> And againe: <hi>Now all are accounted</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Pſ. 47</note> 
                  <hi>Gods people, that beare his sacraments; but all appertaine not to his mercy. For all that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament of the Baptiſme of Chriſt, are called Chriſtians; but all liue not worthily in that Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The like doe other Fathers write, and that worthily. For as <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelf hath obſerued, Chriſts Church is compared in Scripture to a Barne, in which not only wheat, but chaffe alſo is to be found. It is compared to a net that is caſt into the ſea, gathering fiſhes of all ſortes togeather. It is compared to a Nuptiall feaſt, to the which both good and bad are called. It is compared to ten Virgins, fiue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were wiſe, and as many of them fooliſh. It is compared to a ſheepfold, in which are both ſheep and goates. Laſtly it is compared to a great Houſe, wherin are veſſels of al ſorts, ſome vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to honour, and other ſome vnto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="conclusion">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16017:9"/>
               <head>The third Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>OVT of this viſible and Catholike Church, no man can be ſaued, or obtaine remiſſion of Sinnes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1 THIS <hi>Caluin</hi> §. 4. teacheth in theſe words: <hi>Extraeius gremiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nulla eſt ſperanda peccatorum remiſſio, nec vlla ſalus.</hi> Out of her lappe, no remiſſion of ſinnes is to be hoped for, nor any ſaluation at all. And §. 20. <hi>The Lord hath not promiſed his mercy, but in the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saintes.</hi> And §. 22. <hi>This benefite</hi> (to wit of the remiſſion of ſinnes) <hi>is ſo proper vnto the Church, that we cannot otherwiſe enioy it, but by remayning in the communion of it.</hi> And in the ſame place. <hi>Therefore let euery of vs thinke this to be his dutie, not to ſeeke for remiſſion of his ſinnes elſwere, but where the Lord hath put it, to wit, in the viſible Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The ſame teach Catholikes: <hi>He hath not God for his Father</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>)<note place="margin">De Vnita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Eccleſiae</note> 
                  <hi>that hath not the Church for his mother. The holy vniuer ſal Church,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Gregory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 14. Moral. c. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>preacheth, that no man can truly be ſaued, but in her, affirming that all ſuch as are out of her,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16017:9"/> can in no wiſe be ſaued. The Catholike Church</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ep. 50. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Bonifaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Comitenm ſub finen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>only</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Auguſtine) is the body of Chriſt, whoſe Sauiour he is. Out of this body the Holy Ghoſt quickneth no man.</hi> And, <hi>VVhoſoeuer he be, and what manner of man ſoeuer he be, he is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ser. 181 de tempo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re.</note> 
                  <hi>no Chriſtian, that is not in the Church of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Diuers cauſes herof are aſſigned by S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Firſt becauſe in the Church only, the <hi>Hoſt</hi> of the Redeemer is immolated or offered vp. 2. Thoſe that labour in the vineyard only do receiue their penny hire. 3. All that were out of the Arke, were drowned in the floud. 4. That me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber which abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not in the body, cannot haue life. 5. The bough that is cut off from the tree, cannot branch out or grow. 6. A riuer ſeparated from his fountaine dryeth vp. Theſe and the like S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſetteth downe <hi>ſerm. 181. de tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. To the ſame purpoſe is that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſy <hi>Iſa. 60. Open shall thy gates be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">v. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>neither night, nor day shall they be shut, that the ſtrength of the Gentils may be brought vnto thee, and that their Kinges may be brought. For the Nation and the Kingdome that will not ſerue thee, shall perish.</hi> In which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16017:10"/> words there are two things foretold. One is, that Chriſts Church ſhould be viſible, which ſhould be continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly open for all Nations, if they will enter into it. The other is, that all that entred not into it, ſhould periſh.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="conclusion">
               <head>The fourth Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>SVCH as forſake this viſible, and Catholicke Church, are forſakers of Religion, and Traytors and violators of holy VVedlocke.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THVS <hi>Caluin</hi> §. 10. when he ſaith: <hi>So great accompt doth the Lord make of the communion of his Church, that he shall he held a traiterous turne-coate, and forſaker of Religion, whoſoeuer diſobediently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienates himſelfe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Chriſtian ſociety.</hi> And then againe: <hi>VVhence it followeth, that the departing from the Church, is the denying of God and Chriſt, and therfore ſo much the more muſt we beware of ſuch kind of diſagreement, or breach of faith.</hi> And yet againe: <hi>Neither can there be a more heinous crime imagined, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with ſacrilegious diſloyalty, to violate that wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locke, which the only begotten Sonne of God vouchſaſed to contract with vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The like hath <hi>S. Auguſtine lib. de
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16017:10"/> ſide &amp; operibus cap. 5. &amp; lib. 2. contra Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conium cap.</hi> 34. where he teacheth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that the viſible Church (albeit many bad men be in it) is in no wiſe to be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, or deuided. And amongſt other things, he citeth that out of S. <hi>Cyprian.</hi> 
                  <q rend="inline">Although we ſee (ſaith he) cockle to be in the Church, yet ought not our fayth or charity to be hindred, that we ſhould ſtart backe from the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we ſee cockle to be in the Church. We are only to labour, that we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come good corne, that when the corne beginnes to be laid vp in our Lords barnes, we may reape fruite for our worke and labour. The Apoſtle in his Epiſtle ſayth: In a great houſe there are not only great veſsels of gould and ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer; but alſo of wood and earth; and verily ſome are honoured, other ſome diſhonored: Let vs endeauour that we may be a goulden and ſiluer veſſell.</q>
               </p>
               <p>3. And the reaſon appeareth by that which hath beene ſaid, becauſe that out of the Church no man can be ſaued. <hi>Ergo,</hi> he that voluntarily for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaketh the Church, can haue no hope of ſaluation. For he is like a member cut from the body, or a branch cut fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16017:11"/> the Vine, or a ſheep out of the ſheepfold, ſtraying amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g wolues; or like to thoſe, who being out of the Arke, were ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp by the deluge, or floud of waters.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="conclusion">
               <head>The fifth Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THIS viſible Church of Chriſt cannot be without Paſtours, Doctours, Bishops, and other Miniſters, that haue a lawfull calling and ordination.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>SO teacheth <hi>Cal.</hi> §. 11. where he ſaith. <hi>Now doth Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the ſame wickednes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour to deſtroy that miniſtrie, which notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding Chriſt hath ordeined in his Church, that it being taken away, the edificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof might perish.</hi> And <hi>c. 3. §. 4. Phere follow Paſtours and Doctours whome the Church can neuer want.</hi> And in this ſort ſpeak the Fathers. S. <hi>Hierome l. cont. Luciferianos</hi> ſaith: <hi>That is no Church, which hath no Prieſts.</hi> And <hi>S. Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. l. 4. epiſt. 9. Thou oughteſt to know that the Bishop is in the Church, and the Church in the Bishop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; that if any be not with the Bishop, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they in the Church.</hi> And in the ſame place: <hi>The Church is a companie vnited to the Prieſt, and a ſlocke adhering to their Paſtour.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16017:11"/>
               <p>2. And the reaſon hereof is three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. The firſt is, becauſe the Church cannot be without faith. And faith commeth by hearing, <hi>Rom. 10. 14. How shall they inuocate, in whome they haue not belieued? or how shall they belieue him, whom they haue not heard? And how shall they heare without a preacher? or how shall they preach, except they be ſent?</hi> The ſecond rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the Church is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof appertaineth to Biſhops and Paſtours. The third is, becauſe in euery Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth there ought to be order: Some are to gouerne, &amp; others to obey: therfore in like manner in the Church ſome ought to be ſheep, others Paſtours or Sheepheards. Heere hence is that of the <hi>Actes 20. 28. Attend to your ſelues, &amp; to the whole ſlocke, ouer which the Holy Ghoſt hath placed you Bishops, to gouerne the Church of God.</hi> And <hi>Eph. 4. 11. And he gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and other ſome Euangeliſts, and others Paſtours and Doctours, to the conſumation of Saints, vnto the worke of the miniſtrie, vnto the edification of the body of Chriſt.</hi> Vpon which words <hi>Beza Caluins</hi> diſciple writeth thus: <hi>Out of which words it is plaine inough, that theſe two gifts</hi> (to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16017:12"/> wit, of being Paſtours and Doctours) <hi>ought to be perpetuall in the Church of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="conclusion">
               <head>The ſixth Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THIS viſible Church is ſo firmely founded vpon Chriſt, that it cannot poſſibly fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or perish.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THIS <hi>Caluin</hi> cannot deny, becauſe it followeth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly out of his owne principles. This I will ſhew you by theſe argumentes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. Firſt, no man can be ſaued out of the viſible Church, according to the third Concluſion graunted by <hi>Caluin.</hi> But alwaies there are ſome ſaued. <hi>Ergo,</hi> alwayes there is a viſible Church. Secondly, Chriſt conioyned to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the viſible Church, as a Spouſe, with an indiſſoluble band, according to the firſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Concluſion. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church can by no meanes be ſeparated or pulled away from Chriſt. Thirdly It is an article of faith, that a viſible Church be graunted, according to the ſame Concluſion. But articles of faith are alwaies true. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is alwaies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> true, that a viſible Church be granted. Theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:16017:12"/> are out <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Now followeth an argument out of the Scripture, eſpecially out of that place <hi>Matth. 16. 18. Vpon this rocke wil I build my Church, and the gates of Hell shall not preuaile againſt her.</hi> Heere Chriſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth two things. 1. that he will build his Church vpon a rocke. 2. that Hell gates ſhall neuer preuaile againſt her. In both which, he alludeth to that which he had ſaid <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 24. that the wiſe man is he, who buildeth his houſe vpon a rocke; and he a foole, that buildeth on the ſand. And he ſheweth the cauſe why: for that when ſome more violent tempeſt doth ariſe, that houſe which was built vpon the ſand, falleth downe to the ground: but not that which was founded on a rocke. Chriſt then would imitate the wiſe builder, &amp; build his Church vpon a rocke, that by no force of winds or ſtormes, it may be diſturbed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Hereby it appeareth, that ſuch as teach, the Church of Chriſt to haue fallen, or that it may fall, doe great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury vnto Chriſt. For thereupon it plainly followeth, that he built it not vpon a rocke, but on the ſand, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16017:13"/> to haue imitated the fooliſh, not the wiſe builders, yea to haue byn a fabler, in that he promiſed to build it vpon a rocke, and did not: and becauſe he ſaid, the gates of Hel ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt it, and yet haue preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Neither may it be obiected, that Chriſt ſpake of the inuiſible Church. For he plainly ſpeaketh there of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, as <hi>Beza</hi> vpon that place confeſſeth, and others euery where.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The ſame is confirmed by that, <hi>Pſal. 47. 9. God hath ſounded it for euer.</hi> Vpon which place <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> writeth thus. <hi>But perhaps that Citty</hi> (he ſpeaketh of the Church) <hi>which hath held vp the world, shall be ſome time ouerturned? God forbid. God hath ſounded it for euer. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God hath ſounded it for euer, why ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou leaſt the skie should fall?</hi> And v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the 101. <hi>Pſal. concione</hi> 2. diſputing there againſt the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> who ſaid, that the whole viſible Church was periſhed, and remayned only in <hi>Africa,</hi> amongſt certaine iuſt perſons only, he thus ſaith: <hi>But that Church which was of all nations, is now no where, she hath vtterly perished. This they ſay, who are not in her. Oh impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t voice! She is not, becauſe thou art not in
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:16017:13"/> her<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But beware, leaſt thou therfore beeſt not: for the shall be, although thou be not.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he bringeth in the Church ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thus: <hi>How long shal I be in this world? Tell me for their ſake that ſay, she was, but is not now. The Church hath played the Apoſtata, &amp; is peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among all nations: &amp; he told me: Behold I am with you, euen to the end of the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="conclusion">
               <head>The ſeauenth Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THE Roman Church, for the firſt 500. yeares after Chriſt, was that viſible and Catholike Church of Chriſt, wherof we haue hitherto ſpoken.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. THIS Concluſion may be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood two wayes. 1. That the Roman Church, that is, only that Church which was at <hi>Rome,</hi> was Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Vniuerſal. But this is falſe, &amp; is as falſely impoſed vpon vs by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of our Aduerſaries. Secondly that the Roman Church, that is, all that whole multitude of the faithful, which did at that time adhere vnto the Pope, was the Catholike and Vniuerſall Church. This now is true, and <hi>Caluin</hi> confeſſeth as much, when he ſaith, that,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:16017:14"/> 
                  <hi>The Roman Church, was the mother of all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> to wit, becauſe all the particuler Churches of Chriſt, which then were diſperſed ouer the face of the earth, did adhere to the Roman Church, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In this ſenſe the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tooke the Roman Church, &amp; the Catholike Church for one &amp; the ſame: as <hi>S. Hierome cont. Rufinum Apol.</hi> 1. neere the beginning; <hi>Ambroſ. de obitu Satyrifra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris,</hi> &amp; others. Yea, when they would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, &amp; vnfold the Catalogue of ſuch Biſhops as had lawfully ſucceeded one another in the Catholike &amp; Apoſtolike Church; they al waies ſpake of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, &amp; of the ſucceſſion of the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> as appeareth by <hi>Irenaeus, Optatus, Auguſtine, Epiphanius,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis.</hi> For theſe, although they were Biſhops themſelues, to wit, <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riaeus</hi> of <hi>Lions</hi> in <hi>France, Optatus</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> in <hi>Africa, Epiphanius</hi> of <hi>Salamina</hi> in <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prus, Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> yet did they not recount the ſucceſſion of their owne particuler Churches, but of the Roman Church only, to which as to their mother, the other particuler Churches did adhere.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:16017:14"/>
               <p n="3">3. This may be confirmed two waies. Firſt, becauſe after the firſt 300. yeares flouriſhed Pope <hi>Gregory,</hi> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as to their Head, the whole Chriſtian world was conioyned, as appeareth by his Epiſtles which he ſent to all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinces, eſpecially to the Biſhops of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> of <hi>Africke, Spaine, France,</hi> and <hi>Italy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Secondly becauſe after Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> death, was celebrated the ſixt Generall Councell, which our Aduerſaries re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue for moſt holy, as appeareth, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well by others, as alſo by the <hi>Tigurine Confeſſion,</hi> and by the Centuries of the <hi>Magdeburgians.</hi> But it is manifeſtly ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of the ſaid Councell, that the whole <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>VVeſt</hi> at that time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, &amp; conſented with <hi>Agatho</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> as members with their head. For that his ſentence, which by his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates and Epiſtles he declared vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">Cent. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cap. 9.</note> they all followed, as the <hi>Magdeburgians</hi> do record at large.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thus haue we found therfore, that for the firſt 500. yeares, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church was that very company of faithfull people, diſperſed ouer the face of the earth, which did adhere, in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of faith, to the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:16017:15"/> Now we muſt ſee whether in the meane time, there be any thing in this matter changed, or altered.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="conclusion">
               <head>The eight Concluſion.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THE <hi>Church of</hi> Rome <hi>hitherto hath neuer fallen from that ſtate wherin she was the firſt 500. yeares: and therfore as she was the true Catholike and Apoſtolike Church then, ſo is she alſo now.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>1. THIS Concluſion is proued two waies. Firſt <hi>directly,</hi> in this wiſe. The Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Church retaineth ſtil the ſelfe ſame doctrine of faith, &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops, which it had in the firſt 500. yeares. <hi>Ergo,</hi> it is not fallen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſtate, wherin it then was. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly <hi>indirectly,</hi> in this manner. The viſibe Church of Chriſt, and the lawfull ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops, cannot fall on earth, as is already proued out of <hi>Caluin. Ergo</hi> it muſt needs be, that both now there is, and hitherto the viſible Church of Chriſt hath byn vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, with a law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> full ſucceſſion of Biſhops, which in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine conſenteth, or hath conſented with the primitiue Church, which
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16017:15"/> was in the firſt 500. years. But no other Church, beſides the Roman Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either is now, or hath bene hitherto, which either now hath, or hath had a lawfull ſucceſſion of Biſhops, and now conſenteth, or hath conſented with the primitiue Church, in doctrine of faith: <hi>Ergo</hi> the Roman Church now is, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies hath byn the viſible Church of Chriſt on earth. Both which points are now to be explicated.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The explication of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Argument.</head>
                  <p>2. THE former argument contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in it two parts; the one touching the doctrine of faith, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cocerning the ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Biſhops. Our Aduerſaries grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that the ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Biſhops remaineth yet in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe they ſe they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deny it: but they deny the ſelfe ſame doctrine to remaine, which was in the firſt 500. yeares. This is the thing ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore which we are to demonſtrate. But it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be demo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrated more certainly, then by a collation, or comparing of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16017:16"/> the old ancient doctrine, with that of ours, which I do in this manner.</p>
                  <p>3. Whatſoeuer the Roman Church now teacheth, concerning the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall myſteries of our Faith, to wit, of Chriſts reall Preſence in the Euchariſt, of the neceſſitie of baptizing Infants, of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, of Iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of the neceſſity &amp; merit of good works, touching inuocation of Saintes, ſingle life of Prieſts, faſting, ſatisfaction, and Traditions; this was taught heretofore by the primitiue Church, which flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the firſt 500. yeares. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church hath not fallen from the primitiue Church in matters of faith. The Antecedent may be proued two wayes. 1. By an induction, through ech part or member. 2. By the conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or graunt of <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelfe. Both which I will performe in that which followeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The explication of the later Argument.</head>
                  <p>4. THE later Argument hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers parts; only two wherof
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16017:16"/> haue need of proofe. One is, that there is no viſible Church on earth at this time, beſides the Roman, which can haue a lawfull ſucceſſion of Biſhops, or conſent in doctrine of faith with the primitiue Church, which was in the firſt 500. yeares. The other is, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for a 1000. yeares from Pope <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> time, vntil <hi>Martin Luther,</hi> was there any ſuch Church beſides the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. The former part I thus proue. If there were at this time any ſuch Church on earth, beſides the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> without all doubt it ſhould be the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts</hi> Church. But this is not. <hi>Ergo,</hi> there is none but the Roman. The <hi>Maior,</hi> the Caluiniſts (againſt whome I diſpute) do willingly graunt. The <hi>Minor</hi> I proue two waies. Firſt, becauſe the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> Church, which is now extant, neither hath any lawfull Prieſts, or Biſhops; or if it haue any, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not deduce their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion any further the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Luthers</hi> time. <hi>Ergo</hi> it hath failed in the continued ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Biſhops. But the true Church ought to haue a continued, and not an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Biſhops: as we haue before proued out of <hi>Caluin</hi> himſelf. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16017:17"/> becauſe the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> Church co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenteth not in doctrine of faith, with the primitiue Church, which was in the firſt 500. yeares. This againe I will ſhew two waies. Firſt by the graunt of <hi>Galuin</hi> himſelfe. For he plainely confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that he diſſenteth from the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Church in theſe points following.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Touching <hi>Freewill. l. 2. Inſt. c.</hi> 2. §. 4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Concerning <hi>the cooperation of Free-wil with the grace of God. l. 2. c.</hi> 3. §. 7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Touching <hi>Iuſtification. l. 3. c.</hi> 11. §. 15. <hi>Nec Auguſtini quide ſententia recipieda eſt &amp;c.</hi> Neither verily is the opinion of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> to be receiued &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Touching <hi>the perſon of the Mediator. l. 2. c. 14. §. 3. And here the errour of the Aneie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts cannot be excuſed &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Touching <hi>Concupiſcence. l. 3. c. 3. §. 10. Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> opus eſt multu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inueſtigando laborare, quid hic veteres ſenſcrint.</hi> Neither need we la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour much in ſearching out what the old writers haue thought heerin.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Concerning <hi>Satisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. l 2. c. 4. §. 38. But litle do theſe things moue me, which do euery where occurre in the books of the old VVriters.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning <hi>Praier for the dead. l. 3. c. 5. §. 10. VVhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aduerſaries obiect vnto me, that it hath byn receiued by cuſtome aboue 1300. years,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16017:17"/> to pray for the dead</hi> &amp;c. [And a litle after he ſaith that although they ſaw they ſhould not haue don ſo, yet they did ſo. <hi>But the very old Fathers the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues</hi> (ſaith <hi>Caluin) that prayed for the dead, did ſee, that heerin they wanted both commandement of God, &amp; lawfull example.</hi> But who vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Caluins</hi> words wil belieue, that theſe Bleſſed Saints of God, would do that which they yet ſaw was offenſiue vnto God?]</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Touching <hi>Merit. l. 3. c. 15. §. 2. The old writers of the Church</hi> (I confeſſe) <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vſed the word</hi> Merit <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. Touching <hi>Traditions. l. 4. c. 12. §. 23. But this prohibition doth clearly shew how peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferous all traditions are.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. Touching <hi>ſolemne Pennance. l. 4. c. 12. §. 8. In which behalfe the immeaſurable auſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ancient Fathers cannot be excuſed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. Concerning <hi>Lent. l. 4. c. 12. §. 20. At that time the ſuperſtitious obſeruation of Lent, was growne in vſe euery where &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. Touching <hi>Laickes baptizing in time of neceſſity. l. 4. c. 15. §. 20. And that it hath byn for many ages paſt, yea, &amp; in a manner, at the very beginning of the Church, receiued in vſe, that in perill of death Laicks might baptize, I ſee not with how ſtrong a reaſon it may be defended.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. Thus haue I ſhewed you by <hi>Caluins</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:16017:18"/> own grant, that the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> Church diſſenteth in doctrine from the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church. Now I will declare the ſame by this briefe induction.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Caluiniſts do teach,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THAT God is the author of ſinne. <hi>Caluin l. 1. Inst. c. 18. §. 3. And now I haue shewed plainely inough, that God is to be called the author of all thoſe things which theſe Cenſurers wil haue to happen only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> his idle ſufferance.</hi> &amp; §. 4. <hi>Man, by Gods iuſt impulſion, doth that which is not lawfull for him to do.</hi> And §. 1. <hi>Abſolom defiling his Fathers bed with inceſtuous adultery, committed dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable wickednes, yet doth God pronounce this to be his.</hi> And in the ſame place. <hi>VVhatſoeuer men, or Sathan himſelfe do atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt; yet doth God hould the ſterne.</hi> And §. 2. <hi>Satha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ſaid to blind the minds of the vnſaithfull. But whence is this, but that the effectuall working of errour co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from God himſelfe?</hi> And l. 3. c. 23. §. 9. <hi>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate would be thought excuſable, becauſe they cannot eſcape the neceſſity of ſinning: eſpecially ſince by the ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, ſuch neceſſity is caſt vpon them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. That God by his only will did predeſtinate men to eternall death,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:16017:18"/> without any fault or theirs. <hi>Cal. l. 3. c. 21. §. 1. It is euident, that it is wrought by the will of God, that to ſome ſaluation is freely offered; And other ſome are debarred for comming to it.</hi> Et infra. <hi>I his (as many thinke) is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berſome queſtion; becauſe they thinke nothing to be leſſe reaſonable, then out of the common multitude of men<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome to be predeſtinated vnto ſaluation, and other ſome to deſtruction.</hi> And §. 5. <hi>VVe call predeſtination that eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of God, whereby he had it determined with himſelfe, what he willed to become of euery man. For all are not created to a like condition: but to ſome eternall life, to other ſome eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is preordained. Therefore, as to one of theſe two endes euery man is ordayned: ſo we ſay he is predeſtinate either to life, or to death.</hi> And Cap. 22. §. 7. <hi>But whereſoeuer this pleaſure of God raigneth, there no workes come to be conſidered.</hi> And. c. 23. §. 1. <hi>It is in no wiſe meete to aſsigne the preparing to deſtruction to any other thing, then to the ſecret counſel of God.</hi> And §. 2. <hi>Men by the bare will of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their owne deſeruing, are predeſtinate to eternall death.</hi> And §. 5. <hi>I ſay that they were created of the Lord, whome he without doubt foreknew were to goe into deſtruction; and that it was ſo done, becauſe he ſo willed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That Chriſts body is not in the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:16017:19"/> Euchariſt, but in heauen only. <hi>Caluin in his Conſent with the Tigurines in the matter of the Sacrament. All locall imagination of preſence muſt be taken away; ſor when the ſignes are heere in this world, wee ſee them with our eyes, we ſeele them with our handes. Chriſt, as he is man, is no other where to be ſought for, then in heauen, nor otherwiſe then with the mynde, and vnderſtanding of ſaith. Peruerſe therfore &amp; impious ſuperſtition it is, to include him vnder the elements of this world. VVherfore ſuch as in the ſolene words of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> Hoc eſt corpus meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Hic eſt ſangius meus, <hi>do preciſely vrge the litterall ſenſe (as they ſay) let vs reiect them as prepoſterous inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters. For we hold it to be without all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy, that they are to be taken figuratiuely; and that the bread &amp; wine are ſaid to be that which they do ſignify. Neither ought this to ſeeme either new or inſolent, that the name of the thing figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, should by the figure called</hi> Metonymia <hi>be transferred vnto the ſigne; ſeing ſuch like ſpeaches do euery where occurr in Scriptures. Neither do we by ſo ſpeaking, ſay any thing more, then what is extant amongſt all the ancienteſt, &amp; beſt appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued writers of the Church.</hi> And yet againe. <hi>Becauſe the body of Chriſt is finite, &amp; conteined in heauen, as in a place: it muſt needes be ſo far diſtant from vs, as Heauen is from Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:16017:19"/>
                  <p n="4">4. That Baptiſme is not neceſſary to Saluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for children of faithfull pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, becauſe that ſuch childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified from their mothers womb, &amp; are heires of eternal life, through that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>Gen. 17. 7. I will be thy God, and of thy ſeede after thee. Calu. in Antidot. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Trident. ſeſſ. 6. cap. 5. But it hath pleaſed the Councell to driue ſuch Children away from the Kingdome of God, as are firſt taken out of this life, before they could be offered vnto Baptiſme: as though it were ſaid in vaine, that ſuch are borne holy that are borne of faithfull parents? For vnleſſe the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of life should already belong to them before; he should profane Baptiſme, whoſoeuer should giue it them. But if that God haue adopted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto his Kingdome; how great an iniury is there done to the promiſe, as if it were not ſufficient of it ſelfe vnto their ſaluation? The contrary o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion (I confeſſe) hath borne ſway: but it is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt thing that Gods truth should be ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with mans errour, though of neuer ſo long continuance. The ſaluation of children is inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the promiſe, by which God teſtifieth to the faithfull, that he will be a God to them, and to their ſeed. In this reſpect did he pronounce ſuch to be borne vnto him, as came from Abraham. Not from baptiſme therefore hath their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginning, but that which was already founded
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:16017:20"/> in the word, is now ſealed by Baptiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That Originall Sinne is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away by Baptiſme, but ſtill remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth in vs ſo long as we liue. <hi>Cal l. 2. Inſt. c. 1. §. 8. This peruerſneſſe neuer cesſeth in vs.</hi> And. <hi>l.</hi> 4. c. 15. §. 10. <hi>Now it is cleare, how falſe it is, that by baptiſme wee are looſed, and deliuered from Originall ſinne.</hi> And in <hi>Antidoto Conc. Trid. ſeſſ. 5. Sinne truly abideth in vs: neither is it by Baptiſme extinguiſhed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. That only faith doth iuſtifie, and is ſufficient to Saluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Cal. Inſt. l. 3. c. 11. §. 18. VVe ſay that man is iuſtified by ſaith only.</hi> And a little after. <hi>Doth not he perfectly inough giue all things vnto ſaith, that taketh all things fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> workes?</hi> And in <hi>Antid. Conc. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. can. 11. Vim iuſtificandi, ac facultatem fidei in ſolidum vindicamus.</hi> And in the ſame place, <hi>can. 20. VVe are to knowe, that the truſt of Saluation in no wiſe dependeth of keeping the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements. For that ſentence of</hi> Paul <hi>euer ſtandeth, That the Ghoſpell differeth from the Law in this, that it promiſeth life, not vnder the condition of works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as it did, but through Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That all the works of the Iuſt, are defilings &amp; mortal ſinns. <hi>Cal. l. Inſt. 3. c. 12. §. 4. All the workes of men are nothing elſe, but defilings &amp; filthines; &amp; that which amongſt the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſort is accompted righteouſneſſe, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:16017:20"/> God meere iniquity.</hi> And c. 14. §. 9. <hi>Thus haue we shewed, that not ſo much as one good work co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which if it be iudged in it ſelf, deſerueth not the iuſt reward of shame.</hi> And §. 11. <hi>Vpon theſe 2. points we muſt firmely ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that there was neuer yet any work of a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, which if it were examined by the ſeuere Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, was not da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable.</hi> Againe. <hi>If any ſuch worke were shewed (which is not poſſible for man,) yet being corrupted &amp; defiled with ſinne, wherwith moſt certaine it is that the doer of it is burdened &amp; defiled it looſeth grace.</hi> And c. 15. §. 3. <hi>Nothing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of any man, how perfect ſoeuer he be, which is not defiled with ſome ſpot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. That the law of God is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be kept, neither by any man though neuer ſo holy, was it euer yet kept, or can poſſibly be kept hereafter. <hi>Caluin l. 2. Inſt. c. 7. §. 5. VVheras we ſaid the keping of the Law was impoſſible, that is in few words both to be expounded &amp; proued.</hi> And <hi>in Antid. Conc. Trid. ſeſſ. 6. c. 12. It ſufficeth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly that there neuer was any yet, that ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the law of God: neither can there be any ſuch found.</hi> Againe. <hi>He denyeth that the Prophets &amp; Patriarches, &amp; godly Kinges, how ſoeuer they might be holpen by the ſpirit of God, were not meet or able to beare the yoake of the Law: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doth he doubtfully pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that the keeping
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:16017:21"/> of the Law was impoſſible.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. That faith &amp; holineſſe is proper to the elect, &amp; that being once had, it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be loſt any more. <hi>Cal. l. 3. c. 2. §. 11. Therfore as God doth regenerate only the elect with incorruptible ſeed for euer, ſo that the ſeed of life planted in their harts may neuer perish: ſo ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly doth he ſeat the grace of his adoption in them, that it may be ſtable &amp; ſure.</hi> And §. 11. <hi>This in the meane time is to be holden for truth, that how ſmall &amp; weake ſoeuer faith be in the elect; yet becauſe it is a ſure pledge vnto them of the ſpirit of God, and a ſeale of their adoption, the print therof can neuer be blotted out of their harts.</hi> And. c. 24. §. 6. <hi>And neither is this now doubtfull, that Chriſt when he prayeth for all the faithfull, asketh the ſame thing for them, which he asked for Peter, that their ſaith may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fayle: wherby we may gather that they are out of daunger of falling away.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. That indeed God calleth repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates to the faith; but yet with the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall voice only; not by internall grace; neither doth God do it ſeriouſly, and with a purpoſe to help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but feigned<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; with intention to hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Cal. l. 3. c. 24. §. 13. He directeth his voice vnto them, but to the end they may waxe more deafe. He lighteth a light, but that they may be made the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:16017:21"/> blinder. He profers them doctrine, but that they may be more aſtonyshed therby. He applyeth a remedie vnto them, but that they may not be healed. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe &amp; the like do <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> teach. But the primitiue Church in the firſt 500. yeares taught no ſuch thing. Yea, it taught the contrary in all things, as ſhal appeare by the Inductio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> following.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Primitiue Church taught,</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THAT God was not authour of ſinne. <hi>S. Chryſoſtome hom. 2 3. in</hi> Acta Apoſtoloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Let no man ſay, God is to vs author of euills.</hi> Againe. <hi>Better it were to be buried ſix hundred times, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God should heare of ſuch things by vs.</hi> Aug. l. 2. de peccat. meritis c. 17. <hi>Make not God the cauſe of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fault.</hi> Proſp. in reſpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſione ad capitul. Gallor. c. 14. <hi>God is the author of good things, but not of euill things.</hi> Fulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. l. 2. ad Monim. c. 19. <hi>Deus non eſt vltor, cuius eſt author.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing he is reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of Sinnes, he is not authour of them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That God did not predeſtinate any man vnto death, but by reaſon of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:16017:22"/> ſinne. <hi>Aug. l. 3. cont. Iuliannm. c. 18. God is good, &amp; God is iuſt; he can ſaue men without good merits becauſe he is good: but he cannot damne ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without euill merits, becauſe he is iuſt.</hi> And <hi>ad articulos falso ſibi impoſitos art. 2. That men are borne, it is a good turne; but it is the fault of the preuaricator, that they perish.</hi> Tertul. in libro de reſurrectione carnis, <hi>Deus de ſuo optimus eſt, de noſtro iuſtus.</hi> Fulgentius l. 1. ad Monimun. c. 26. <hi>It is well knowne there can not be ſaid to be Gods wrath, but where ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s iniquitie is belieued to haue gone before.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Body and Bloud of Chriſt is truly and really in the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, <hi>Hilarius. l 8. de Trinit. Concerning the verity of the flesh &amp; bloud there is left no place of doubt.</hi> Cyril. Hieroſolymitan. Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſ. 4. <hi>VVhen Chriſt himſelfe ſo affirmeth, &amp; ſaith of the bread,</hi> Hoc eſt corpus meum, <hi>who dare afterwards doubt therof?</hi> And in the ſame place: <hi>Vnder the forme of bread his body is giuen thee, &amp; vnder the forme of wine there is giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his bloud.</hi> &amp; infra. <hi>Holding this for moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that this bread, which we ſee, is not bread, though the taſt iudge it to be bread, but the body of Chriſt.</hi> Ambroſius l. 4. de Sacrament is c. 4. <hi>VVhen the conſecration is made of bread it becomes the body of Chriſt.</hi> And in lib. de myſterijs initia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dis c. 9. <hi>Perhaps thou wilt
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:16017:22"/> ſay; I ſee another thing: how telleſt thou me, that shall receiue the body of Chriſt? And this point remaines yet, that we proue it &amp;c.</hi> [Aug. ſerm. 28. de verbis Domini, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the words of Chriſt, that which is offered is called bread, but when the wordes of Chriſt are vttered, it is no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger called bread,</hi> ſed COR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PVS appellatur.]</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That Baptiſme for Infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to ſaluation. <hi>Aug. l. 3. de anima &amp; cius origine c. 9. Belieue not, ſay not, teach not, that children preuented by death, before they be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, can attaine to the pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of originall ſinne, if thou wilt be a Catholike.</hi> And epiſt. 28. ad Hieronymum: <hi>VVhoſoeuer shall ſay, that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch children shall be quickened in Chriſt, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part this life without participation of his Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this man verily condemneth the whole Church.</hi> Let al Caluiniſts liſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That originall ſinne is taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by Baptiſme. <hi>Aug. Conc. 1. in Pſal. 115. That as the Aegyptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were drowned in the ſea, ſo are our ſinns droumed and extinct in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, the Prophet doth intimate more clearely then the light it ſelfe, ſaying: He will caſt all our ſinns into the depth of the ſea.</hi> Amb. l. 2. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cram. c. 4. <hi>VVorthily is that water ſweet, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our fault is ſwallowed vp.</hi> Lactantius. l. 3. c. 26. <hi>By one lauare is all euill abolished.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:16017:23"/>
                  <p n="6">6. That faith without works and the keeping of the commandements is not ſufficient to ſaluation. <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinui l. 5. ſtromatum. By grace we are ſaued, but yet not without good workes.</hi> Nazra. orat. in ſanctum lauacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Doe good, becauſe that faith without workes is dead.</hi> Chryſoſt. ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. lib. 3. in Ioan. <hi>Doth it ſuffice vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life to belieue in the Sonne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> No, it doth not, ſaith he. S. Hierome in cap. 26. Iſaiae. Let a wall, &amp; a forewall be ſet therin. The wall of good works, &amp; the forewall of Faith. For it is not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to haue a wall of faith, vnleſse that ſaith it ſelfe be ſtrengthned by good works.</hi> Aug. in lib. de fide &amp; operibus. <hi>Now let vs ſee that which muſt be shaken out of all religious harts, leaſt by an euill ſecurity they looſe their ſaluation, if they shall thinke only ſaith to be ſufficient for the obtaining of it &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. That the works of the Iuſt are meritorious before God. <hi>Aug. ſerm. 102. de tempore.</hi> Deus pro meritis ſidei a tque bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> operum dabit ſuis fidelibus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum caeloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>God for the merits of faith &amp; of God works will giue vnto his faithfull children the Kingdome of Heauen.</hi> Baſil. orat. in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium Prouerbiorum. <hi>All we that walke the way of the Ghoſpell, are merchants; getting vnto our ſelues the poſſeſſion of heauen, by the workes
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:16017:23"/> of the commaundements.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. That the law of God is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. <hi>Baſil. in illud</hi> Attende tibi. <hi>It is a wicked thing to ſay that the Commaundements are impoſſible.</hi> Chryſoſt. hom. 8. de poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia. <hi>Doe not accuſe our Lord; he commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not impoſſible things.</hi> S. Hier. l. 3. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr. Pelagianos. <hi>God hath commaunded things that are poſſible: this no man doubteth.</hi> Aug. l. de natura &amp; gratia, c. 43. <hi>God therfore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth not impoſſible things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. That faith, &amp; holineſſe being once had, may yet be loſt againe: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it proper to the elect only. <hi>Aug. in lib. de corrept. &amp; gratiac. 13. VVe muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, that ſome of the Children of perdition, (hauing not receiued the gift of perſeuerance to the end) haue begun to liue in that faith, which worketh by charity, and do for ſome while liue both faithfully and iuſtly, and afterwards fall.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. That God by his internall grace calleth al, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprobates vnto the faith, &amp; as much as lieth in him ſeeketh their ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Ambr. ſerm. 8. in Pſal. 118. The Sun of Iuſtice is riſen vnto all, comen vnto all, ſuffered for all, and roſe againe for all. But if any belieue not in Chriſt, he defraudeth himſelfe of as general a benefit, as if a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hauing his win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes shut, should barre forth the beames of the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:16017:24"/> Sunne,</hi> Chryſoſt. hom. 7. in leremiam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>He enlighteneth euery man, as much as in him lyeth. But if any voluntarily (the eyes of their mind being cloſed) will not direct their eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight vnto the beames of this light, ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt not in darkeneſſe by reaſon of the light, but through their own malice or fault.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now thou ſeeſt, Good Reader, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> Church teacheth one thing, and the Primitiue Church another thing, in matters of ſayth, <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin</hi> himſelfe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth as much; &amp; it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly appeareth by theſe few things, which we haue alledged. Wherupon I conclude that which was to be proued, viz. that the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> Church at this time is not the true Church of Chriſt, becauſe that it diſagreeth from the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue Church, which all men graunt was the true Catholike, &amp; Apoſtolike Church, <hi>Ergo</hi> the Roman Church is the Catholike Church.</p>
                  <p>Hitherto haue we ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part. The latter is, that for the ſpace of a 1000. yeares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> vntil <hi>Mart. Luther,</hi> there was no viſible Church but the Roma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which had a lawful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops, &amp; conſent with the primitiue Church in doctrin of faith.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:16017:24"/> This needs no proof, becauſe the <hi>Calui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> can aſſigne forth no ſuch Church, beſides the Roman. Or if they thinke that they can, I intreat the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhew vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, who were the Doctors of that Church? who were the Biſhops &amp; Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours? who were the Martyrs? what Kings &amp; Emperours adhered vnto it? what heretikos were caſt forth by it? What Vniuerſities were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by it? what Churches it builded? To none of theſe can they anſwere any other thing but that they know not, or ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tell.</p>
                  <p>But I wil vrge them further. If there were any viſible Church for theſe 1000. yeares, either it was knowne or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to men. If it were knowne, name then the Doctours &amp; Biſhops therof. Name the Prouince, Citty, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, wherin it was? Who hath reueiled this matter vnto you? None of you ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in thoſe dayes. And to them that liued then, it was vnknowne, you ſay. By what meanes then know you, that ſuch a Church there was? Heere you are plunged, and ſticke faſt. And ſtill I tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, vntil you giue me an anſwere. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore once againe I conclude, that there neither now is, nor hath bene hitherto
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:16017:25"/> any viſible Church, beſides the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which hath agreed with the Primitiue Church, in matters of faith, and had a lawfull ſucceſſion of Biſhops.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16017:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
